# **Usama Jahangir**

J +92-313-6112460 | ■ mr.usama.jahangir@gmail.com | Im/usama-jahangir | Head Portfolio | Google Scholar

## **PROFILE**

Mechatronics Engineer with  $\sim$ 2 years of industry experience, specializing in embedded firmware and algorithm design. Led the development of 2 Al-powered robots and contributed to a Level 2 ADAS, 2 IoT products, and 5 embedded Android applications.

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

Robotics and Autonomous Systems, Sensor Fusion, Embedded Systems, Human-Robot Interaction, Edge Computing

## **EDUCATION**

## National University of Sciences and Technology &

Islamabad, Pakistan

BEng. Mechatronics Engineering (CGPA: 3.66, Rector's Gold Medal)

Graduation Date: Jun 2023

**Extra Coursework:** Machine Learning, Control Systems, Robotics, Artificial Neural Network & Advance Embedded Systems **Senior Year Research Project:** Assistive Feeding System, Vision-Guided Feeding Robot (Conference Publication ICRAl'24)

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Software Motion &

Suzhou, China (Remote)

Algorithm Engineer

Dec 2024 - Present

- Contributing to object and ego-motion modules of Level 2 ADAS by fusing camera and radar data for ACC, AEB, and LCC.
- Designed algorithms for lane line fusion (Kalman Filters) and tracking (Track-to-Track Association) for LAC & LDW using C.

## Cowlar Design Studio (Y-Combinator Backed)

Islamabad, Pakistan

Team Lead, Industrial Automation

Sep 2024 - Oct 2024

- · Led a team of 5 to automate optical fiber assembly processes using Al-powered robots, resulting in a 4x throughput increase
- Directed client communication, weekly meetings, and task delegation to deliver mission-critical support for production robots
- Contributed to component integration, control logic, and data flow utilizing Python, Docker, and Rockchip's RK3588

#### Embedded Design Engineer

Jun 2023 - Aug 2024

- Led prototype development of a fiber insertion robot with 250-micron precision in 15 days, leading to a successful demo
- · Collaborated with a cross-functional team of over 50, contributing to five Android applications using Kotlin and C
- Developed the "Sensor App" from scratch, integrating IMU, cameras, and barcode scanners, deployed in smart carts
- Automated deployments with Docker and Shell-based GitLab runners, improving pipeline efficiency by up to 60%
- · Created automation scripts for testing and maintenance using Python and Shell scripting, streamlining operational efficiency

## Qadri Group &

Lahore, Pakistan

## Leaders for Manufacturing Intern

Jul 2022 - Sep 2022

- Conducted ergonomic analysis & tested fixture designs to improve labor output for three parts, increasing throughput by 33%
- · Collaborated with a team of 3 and presented feasibility reports and solutions, driving informed decision-making

## National Centre of Robotics and Automation *9*

Rawalpindi, Pakistan Jul 2021 - Aug 2021

Biomedical Research & Development Intern

Restored a 3D-printed, parallel manipulator-based "Upper Limb Prosthesis," enhancing control for people with amputations

· Programmed linear actuators in C, enabling multi-grasp capabilities to support dexterity and usability for prosthesis users

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

**Usama Jahangir**, Fahad Aamir, Wajid Ali, Mohsin Tiwana, Hamid Jabbar. (2024). "Assistive Feeding System: Design and Evaluation" Proceedings of the 6th IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation in Industry

## **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

**Software Development:** Python, C, C++, Kotlin, Shell Scripting, Android SDK, Docker, GitLab Cl/CD, Git, REST APIs **Embedded Systems:** Protocols (CAN, I2C, UART, SMBus, MQTT), ESP32, FreeRTOS, SoC (BCM2711, RK3588, SG865W)

**Robotics & AI:** ROS2, Sensor Fusion (LKF, EKF), Computer Vision (OpenCV, YOLO), Sensor Integration **Simulation & Prototyping:** Proteus, SOLIDWORKS, ANSYS, 3D Printing (FDM), MATLAB/Simulink

## **PROJECTS**

**Fiber Termination Line:** Led the development of an AI-powered 5-stage optical fiber assembly robot, leveraging Python & OrangePi to reduce processing time by 80% (from 60 to 12 minutes). Deployed 1 unit on the production floor.

**Fiber Sorting Robot:** Contributed to sensor integration and control system design for automated fiber sorting using Python & OrangePi, achieving 30x faster operation (from 240 to 8 seconds). Five robots deployed to assist in production.

**Assistive Feeding System:** Led a team of 3 to develop a vision-guided 6 DoF serial robotic manipulator to assist in feeding tasks by using hybrid methods for 3D localization and kinematic modelling. Successfully fed rice to 3 test users.

**Indigenous Harvesting Robot:** Led a team of 6 to design and develop a mobile robot to harvest fruits with line and wall following features using C and ATMega328P, competed at national-level in NERC'22 to the quarterfinals.

Wearable Exo-Glove: Developed a TPU-based tendon-driven exo-glove as an assistive device for stroke patients using FDM.

Serial USB Driver: Developed a driver in C using JNI to map tty device paths, enabling USB detection for custom devices.

**SMBus:** Implemented SMBus over I2C on ESP32 using C and FreeRTOS, debugged a protocol error using a logic analyzer within the official BQ40Z50 manual. Enabled data acquisition from smart cart batteries.

Chess 1.0: Created a CLI-based game with graphics using C++, enhancing user engagement through interactive gameplay.

#### **AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS**

Houston Award (Cowlar, 2024): Awarded for exceptional leadership and contributions in the Industrial Automation sector.

National Grassroots ICT Research Grant (IGNITE, 2024): Received grant of PKR 54,618 for "Assistive Feeding System."

News Coverage (2024): Presented "Assistive Feeding System" on 5 National television interviews, including ARY News etc.

Rector's Gold Medal (NUST, 2023): Received for the best capstone project in the Dept. of Mechatronics Engineering, NUST.

1st Prize (COMMPEC, 2023): Winner in the electromechanical system category in this national-level competition.

Distinguished Student Award (NUST, 2022, 2023): For securing an SGPA above 3.5 for four or more consecutive semesters.

#### **VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE**

## Robotics and Automation Club Mentor & Advisor

Rawalpindi, Pakistan Sep 2021 - Jun 2023

- Mentored over 50 cross-department students through 3D printing and a series of programming workshops for robotics beginners.
- Led a team of 3 mentor to structure the learning material for workshop series on programming, 3D printing and electronics.

#### REFERENCES

## Dr. Umar Shahbaz Khan

Professor, National University of Sciences and Technology, u.shahbaz@ceme.nust.edu.pk, +92-300-5533775

#### Dr. Hamid Jabbar

Associate Professor, National University of Sciences and Technology, hamid.jabbar@ceme.nust.edu.pk, +92-300-5274026

## Mr. Hamza Naeem

Co-Founder & SVP Robotics and Automation, Cowlar Design Studio, hamza@cowlar.com, +1-617-238-4508